<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints fulnesse of joy in their fellowship with God presented in a sermon preached July 21. 1646. before the Honorable House of Commons in Margarets Westminster, being the day appointed for thankesgiving for the surrender of Oxford. By the least of saints, and the meanest of the ministers of the Gospel, W. Cradock.</title>
            <author>Cradock, Walter, 1606?-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897055</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2464:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints fulnesse of joy in their fellowship with God presented in a sermon preached July 21. 1646. before the Honorable House of Commons in Margarets Westminster, being the day appointed for thankesgiving for the surrender of Oxford. By the least of saints, and the meanest of the ministers of the Gospel, W. Cradock.</title>
                  <author>Cradock, Walter, 1606?-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Matthew Simmons, and are to be sold by George VVhittington, at the blew Anchor neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verso of first leaf contains author's appointment to print, with reference to a Parliamentary order to print.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the late thanksgiving, before the Commons House of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Oxford (England) --  History --  Siege, 1645 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133226:1"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS FULNESSE OF JOY in their fellowſhip with God: PRESENTED In a Sermon preached <hi>July</hi> 21. 1646.</p>
            <p>Before the Honorable Houſe of Commons in <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtminſter, Being the day appointed for Thankeſgiving for the ſurrender of OXFORD.</p>
            <p>By the leaſt of Saints, and the meaneſt of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, <hi>W. Cradock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>George VVhittington,</hi> at the blew Anchor neere the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment_of_printers">
            <pb facs="tcp:133226:2"/>
            <p>THere was an Order from the Honorable Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to print this Diſcourſe, ſuch as it is, allowing me the uſuall priviledges vouchſafed in this kind; in obedience to which Order, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point <hi>Matthew Simmons</hi> and <hi>Hannah Allen</hi> to print the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:133226:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133226:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133226:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HONORABLE Houſe of Commons, ASSEMBLED IN</hi> PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>EACE among Brethren is the Pearle that is loſt in theſe dayes; which many pretend to ſeek, and all juſtly complaine is wanting; many out-cryes there are for it, in the mouth's of ſome, whoſe hearts and principles are full of warre and contention; <hi>Their words are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55. 21.</note> 
               <hi>ſofter then oyle, and yet they be drawne ſwords;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:133226:4"/> Yea ſuch is the hypocriſie of this age, that it is become al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the <hi>Character</hi> of a Malignant, or Atheiſt, in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, with much ſeeming zeale and devotion, to pray and deſire <hi>Peace, Union, Reconciliation,</hi> neglecting the while all meanes that may conduce to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Others there are (and thoſe not a few) who long for <hi>Peace,</hi> and that ſincerely, but not hitting the right way to attaine to it, doe often caſt more Oyle into the flame, and make the breach wider. This following <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> (though it be the meaneſt of any that ever hath been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto you) points out the ſureſt and readieſt way to finde this Jewel, <hi>(i.) Fellowſhip with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Fellowſhip with God neceſſarily begets fellowſhip between men. He onely is an enemy to <hi>Man,</hi> that is not upon tearmes of friendſhip with <hi>God. God is love,</hi> and when we are in him, and walke with him, wee cannot but be like him. Could wee fully appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>God</hi> as our <hi>Father, Chriſt</hi> as our <hi>Head,</hi> all the <hi>Saints</hi> his <hi>members,</hi> choſen and beloved, wee ſhould no longer <hi>bite,</hi> teare, and devoure one another: a ſpirit of Love, Goodneſſe, Meekneſſe, Long-ſuffering, that is in <hi>God,</hi> and dwells in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would run through all our veines; tempering our hearts, and framing our carriages <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euk.</hi> 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</note> towards men, as God's in Chriſt hath been towards us. Yea, it would mollifie our ſpirits towards all, even the worſt of men, and make us <hi>live peaceably as much as in us lieth with all men. To give no offence to any man.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>To ſpeake evill of no man. To bleſſe when wee are blaſphemed. To give up our cloakes to him that takes away our coat,</hi> &amp;c. And becauſe there is a generall diſtance growne between men and God, an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion
<pb facs="tcp:133226:4"/> of ſpirituall fellowſhip, therefore theſe Scriptures are become now <hi>Apocryphall,</hi> which were precious Truths formerly to the Saints, (and it may be ſtill are to a few) who ſtudied rather to conforme themſelves to the ſtricteſt <hi>Rules,</hi> then wreſt the <hi>Rule</hi> to their owne carnall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and corrupt luſts; a practice too common in theſe times.</p>
            <p>Oh that wee could then doe as the wiſe Traveller, who being wilderd in a Forreſt, deſpairing to finde the way forward, returnes thither where he firſt loſt his way: We have loſt our way, our ſelves, our God, and all almoſt, by an <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-violent</hi> contention about Things <hi>externall:</hi> Wee have caſt durt upon each other, that will not be wiped off our names in many Ages, opened the mouth's of the wicked, rejoyced the hearts of Papiſts, grieved the Spirit of God. Oh how happy ſhould wee <hi>yet</hi> be, if wee would returne to our GOD, renewing our fellowſhip with him in the Spirit!</p>
            <p>Surely it was better with us then when wee made our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>Fellowſhip with God, Holineſſe, Righteouſneſſe,</hi> our chiefe ſtudie, when <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> was the <hi>Cement</hi> that united us together; When wee were <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from the world, and knowne to one another by the ſtyle of <hi>Saints, Profeſſors of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Honeſt-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is one of my firmeſt Principles, and by Gods Grace ſhall ever be my practice, to make <hi>union and communion with God my maine worke, to ſtudie peace with all men; To Love, Honour, Receive SAINTS</hi> quà <hi>SAINTS;</hi> To receive, I ſay, thoſe whom Chriſt hath received. The God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:133226:5"/> binde up every one of your ſoules in that bundle, and ſo preſerve your whole ſpirit, ſoule and body blameleſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his comming, which ſhall ever be the moſt unfeigned prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant, W. CRADOCK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133226:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED at the late Thankeſgiving, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Honourable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS,</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 IOHN 1. 3, 4.</bibl>
               <q>And truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. And theſe things write wee unto you, that your joy may be full.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chiefe end (Beloved) of your meeting here this day is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce together, for thoſe manifold mercies, that the Lord hath been pleaſed to beſtow (of late eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) upon you and the whole Kingdom; and I ſuppoſe that we (I meane the Miniſters) that are called hither by you, are intended to be (as the Scripture ſaith) as <hi>furtherers of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 25.</note> 
               <hi>your joy.</hi> But truly, Beloved, thoſe mercies of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that are in your thoughts, and that have been ſpoken of here already at large, (I meane thoſe victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſurrenders of Garriſons &amp;c.) though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133226:6"/> they be very great, and glorious, yet they may in a ſort be reckoned among naturall things, they are at beſt but temporall mercies, and ſo they can produce but a kind of naturall joy. For as wee heard this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>vide.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilkinſons</hi> Sermon.</note> 
               <hi>the effect muſt be, as the cauſe is.</hi> And as it is ſomewhat beneath a Chriſtian to inſiſt much upon thoſe naturall things, thereby to expreſſe naturall affections; ſo is it much more below the worke of a Goſpel Miniſter to ſtir you up to ſuch joyes as theſe things doe properly produce. Therefore my deſigne at this time is (as God ſhall inable me) to raiſe you up a little above all theſe things, to lead you to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall joy, which indeed is the onely true joy, at leaſt the fountaine of all joy. For take any other joy and abſtract it from its <hi>ſpiritualities,</hi> then indeed you may ſay of it with <hi>Solomon,</hi> it is but as the <hi>crackling of thornes;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eeles. 7. 6.</note> it is light, ſhort, ſuperficiall, and will undoubtedly end in everlaſting ſorrow. Therefore as I would not put you out of your way of rejoycing, ſo I wiſh I could ſcrue you up to the trueſt joy, that is, to the moſt ſpirituall joy, which is fully laid downe here in my text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. And theſe things write wee unto you, that your joy may be full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in this Epiſtle writes to Saints, though he doth not deſcribe, or decipher them by their names, condition, or the places of their habitation, (as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> and other Apoſtles doe) yet he ſtyles them by a glorious title, <hi>viz. Beleivers,</hi> as you may ſee 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you that beleive on the name of the Sonne of God &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in writing thus to beleivers, his ſcope as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133226:6"/> was twofold, or he aimes principally at two things, as you may clearely ſee if you peruſe the whole Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to build them up in their holy faith, to raiſe their faith to an higher pitch, or degree, whereby they might have, and injoy, <hi>more fellowſhip with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and ſo by conſequence <hi>be more joyfull, holy, and obedient.</hi> This you ſhall ſee if you compare 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 13. with this 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The other thing that the Apoſtle aimes at is, <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Chriſtian and ſpirituall love betweene one beleiver and another.</hi> And this he ſpeakes much of throughout the Epiſtle, eſpecially in the 3. and 4. <hi>chap.</hi> I ſhall not at all at this time meddle with this latter, my buſineſſe lieth wholly in the former.</p>
            <p>Now the only <hi>meanes and way</hi> that the Apoſtle here takes to attaine to this his aime is <hi>by diſcovering, or lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open Jeſus Chriſt clearely and fully unto them,</hi> as we ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>That which was from the beginning, which wee have heard, which wee have ſeen with our eyes, which wee have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of life &amp;c.</hi> He takes this as the chiefe meanes, to build them up in faith, joy, love, and holineſſe; a diſcovery (I ſay,) or laying open of Jeſus Chriſt unto them: and that not ſimply or carnally, but in his ſpirituality and glory. And therefore he uſeth an <hi>elogie</hi> for his perſon which of all other is the moſt comprehenſive that I know in Scripture, he calls him the <hi>Word:</hi> and then <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> withall he ſets him out with his graces, and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges we have by him, comprehending them all in the word <hi>Eternall life.</hi> For as of all the titles that doe expreſſe the perſonall excellencies of the Lord Chriſt that is the moſt glorious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the word:</hi> ſo of all that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133226:7"/> hold forth the priviledges that wee have by him, there is not one word that expreſſeth them ſo fully as this of <hi>Eternall life;</hi> for it containes, and comprehends all the grace and glory wee have with him. This is the courſe and meanes that he takes to wind up the Saints to a higher pitch of faith, holineſſe &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Neither doeth he propoſe Chriſt to them (though in his glory) as a thing uncertaine, but he ſets him forth with a great deale of <hi>evidence</hi> and <hi>aſsurance;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <hi>That which was from the begininng, which we have HEARD, which we have SEEN with our eyes, which we have looked upon &amp;c.</hi> The meaning is not properly, that <hi>John</hi> having been an Apoſtle with Chriſt, did ſometimes handle him, &amp; ſometimes lay in his boſome, and ſo this to be underſtood in a <hi>corporall way;</hi> but the meaning I conceive is this, <hi>we have knowne Jeſus Chriſt, he hath been ſo revealed to us, with that fulneſſe of aſsurance, with that perſpicuity and cleareneſſe; that as in naturall things, you have many ſenſes concur together, to diſcover them, as eyes, eares, hands, &amp;c. theſe things are very ſure and certaine: ſo (Brethren) ſaith</hi> John, <hi>that I may build you up in faith &amp;c. I would lay open Jeſus the word of God, that hath eternall life with him, as a thing that is as ſure, and certaine, as if yee had ſeene him, and taſted him, heard him, and handled him, as wee our ſelves have done;</hi> for as Jeſus Chriſt by the Spirit of God had been made knowne in that cleare manner with that certainty to <hi>John,</hi> ſo he goeth about to cleare him with the ſame aſſurance alſo to other beleivers, that <hi>they alſo might have fellowſhip with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as he had. I will detaine you no longer in the coherence of the words.</p>
            <p>In the words themſelves there are three things to be obſerved.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:133226:7"/>
            <p> Firſt, <hi>an Aſſertion,</hi> our <hi>fellowſhip is with the Father,</hi> and <hi>his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is a glorious one, as any I know in this bleſſed booke.</p>
            <p>Secondly, an <hi>Aſſeveration</hi> (if I may ſo call it,) to this bleſſed <hi>Aſſertion, TRVLY</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father &amp;c.</hi> though I confeſſe the <hi>Greeke</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not ſo emphaticall as our word <hi>[truly]</hi> in Engliſh, yet as it ſtands here in its <hi>coherence</hi> comparing it with the beginning of the chapter, and obſerving the <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency</hi> of his expreſſion, we <hi>have ſeen and taſted and handled the word of life,</hi> we may well call <hi>[truly]</hi> a kind of <hi>Aſseveration</hi> to this <hi>Aſſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>end</hi> that the Apoſtle hath to ſpeake thus highly of this his fellowſhip, is not out of pride, or vaine-glory, as the <hi>Phariſee Luke</hi> 18. <hi>I thanke God I faſt twice in the weeke, I am not as other men. John</hi> did not ſpeake thus out of pride of ſpirit when he ſaith, <hi>Truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> as if he ſhould meane all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are punyes or carnall people in compariſon of himſelf: no, but with humility and love, out of a deſire to doe my brethren good; theſe <hi>things I write unto you that your joy may be full;</hi> I write not theſe things to boaſt of, and make a ſhew, but I am forced to write theſe things becauſe I ſee with ſo much certainty the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency that is in Jeſus Chriſt, and doe taſte ſo much ſweetneſſe in communion, and fellowſhip with him, that I cannot chuſe but write thus unto you that you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may have fellowſhip with him. I will ſtand no longer upon the explication and diviſion of the words, there is enough already ſaid to lead us to many wholſome bleſſed truthes that lie in and about theſe words, if God give us his Spirit, and we had time to looke into them;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133226:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> there are many truthes (I ſay) that well become <hi>Iohn the Divine,</hi> as he is called; they are all <hi>divine,</hi> tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <hi>divine</hi> and ſpirituall: I will only touch 3. or 4. Obſervations, and then pitch upon one.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The more ſpirituall or divine Chriſtians are, the more</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>they wilbe taken up and imployed about ſpirituall worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> is called <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Divine,</hi> not as wee call <hi>Divines</hi> from Office, but from the excellency of Grace, and the cleareneſſe of divine manifeſtations, therefore the Ancients compare him to an <hi>Eagle;</hi> now <hi>John</hi> in his whole Epiſtle medleth not with controverſies, (eſpecially about outward and externall things,) but being wholly ſpirituall, he writes altogether ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, about <hi>ſpirituall ſubſtantiall</hi> things from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end. Miſtake me not, I doe not ſay that it is not lawfull, and ſometime convenient, for Miniſters and others to have to doe with ſuch things but this is that I only ayme at; whereas divers conceive that it is their ſpiritualneſſe, the excellency of their grace, that they are carried on in <hi>Pulpits</hi> and <hi>Preſſes</hi> ſo vehemently in wrangling and ſtriving about external things, it is to be feared that much of that zeale, violence, and labour is fleſhly; and were wee more ſpirituall, hundreds (I beleive) of thoſe Queſtions would be removed, that lie now like ſtumbling blocks in our way, according to that in the 2. of this <hi>Epiſt. ver.</hi> 10. <hi>He that loves his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abideth in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in him.</hi> And were wee filled with the knowledge of God, the love of Chriſt, humility and ſelfe-deniall, preferring each other before our ſelves; certainely a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133226:8"/> world of theſe controverſies would ſoone vaniſh away: As thoſe that are <hi>ſpirituall</hi> can ſpeake by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing I would have you to obſerve, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beſt way to bring either a Sinner to God, or to build up a Saint, in any grace, or in any point of godlineſſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>is the ſpirituall promulgation, manifeſtation or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Jeſus Chriſt in his perſon, excellencies and Priviledges, doings and ſufferings &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the beſt meanes; therefore <hi>John</hi> uſeth onely that, he layes down Jeſus Chriſt as one that had beene <hi>ſeene, heard,</hi> &amp; <hi>felt,</hi> (as it were) to be the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the eternall word that brought eternal life, and he expects that this ſhould worke in the ſoule <hi>faith, joy &amp;c.</hi> I beſeech you beare with mee beloved, I feare we ſpend a great deale of our time almoſt in vaine, and waſte much of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, when we would bring our owne hearts, or others to a duty, or ſtir up a grace, we uſe and urge ſo many <hi>morall Motives</hi> and <hi>Meanes;</hi> not that I ſay but wee may uſe motives and meanes ſpirituall and morall, but if we did ſtudy to open Ieſus Chriſt fully to the ſoule, <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 14.</note> if we did lift up the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> ſo as poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might behold him, we ſhould not need the tenth part of thoſe meanes, exhortations, and paines that we now take: For in the Goſpel wee ſhall ſee (and it is our wiſdome to follow the ſcripture; the neerer that, the better) the Apoſtles when they went forth to preach they told them a ſtory (if I may ſo ſpeake with reverence) <hi>of one Jeſus Chriſt that was the word of God, and that was become man, and how he was crucified at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and how he was raiſed from the dead,</hi> and all this in a plaine, ſimple, ſpirituall way and manner, and while
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133226:9"/> they were telling theſe bleſſed ſtories, the Spirit fell upon people, and they beleived, and had faith wrought in them. Faith is not wrought ſo much in a rationall way, (I meane in a way of ratiocination) as by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God comming upon the ſoules of people by the relation, or repreſentation of Chriſt to the ſoule; and this our Lord himſelfe hintes. <hi>As Moſes lifted up the Serpent in the wilderneſſe, even ſo muſt the Sonne of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>man be lifted up, that whoſoever beleiveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> You know the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the brazen <hi>Serpent,</hi> when people were ſtung, God ſo ordered it that the <hi>very beholding</hi> ſhould bring help (though we know not how) to thoſe that were wounded, and ſtung by thoſe <hi>Serpents:</hi> ſo God hath ordained in his bleſſed wiſdome that the <hi>diſcovery</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>beholding</hi> of him, the <hi>eying</hi> of him by faith, ſhould be that, which ſhall transforme us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his image, and ſo conforme us to any duty, as the Apoſtle ſaith, wee are <hi>transformed while wee behold him with open face to his glory.</hi> Hence it is that in Scripture <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> all godlineſſe and every point of godlineſſe, is often called the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> For inſtance, <hi>juſtification</hi> in Scripture is called the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt; By his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lede ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtifie many.</hi> So alſo <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 53.</note> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>Grow in grace &amp; in the knowledge of Chriſt. After that by the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt they were cleanſed from their ſins &amp;c.</hi> Truly, Beloved, every grace is <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> comprehended in the <hi>knowledge</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, did we know Jeſus Chriſt aright, ſavingly, ſpiritually, effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, we ſhould be full of faith, full of godly feare, full of humility, full of ſelf-deniall, full of diligence, and readines to every good word and worke, ſo that our maine defect is in that, but I paſſe by that alſo.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:133226:9"/>
            <p> A third thing be pleaſed to obſerve from the cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of theſe words, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Divine objects, ſeene by faith (if it be a ſaving and right faith,) carries with them as much evidence, certainty, and aſſurance, as any naturall thing that wee apprehend by any, or all our naturall ſenſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We have ſeen, heard, and taſted,</hi> the more of our ſenſes are imployed to apprehend a thing, the more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, confidence, and evidence it carries with it. Put the five ſenſes together to diſcover any naturall object whatſoever, that cannot be more ſure and certaine to us, then all ſpirituall objects apprehended by a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chriſtian, through a lively faith, are to him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid that faith is the <hi>evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1.</note> of things <hi>inviſible;</hi> he doth not ſay that faith is an <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> a <hi>probability, a conjecture</hi> or a <hi>wild gueſſe,</hi> but faith (ſaith he) is the <hi>evidence</hi> of things not ſeen, that is, of things that by naturall reaſon you cannot ſee, yet making them as <hi>reall</hi> and as <hi>evident</hi> as any thing wee doe ſee by reaſon, ſenſe, and all.</p>
            <p>And thence (Beloved) you ſee that godly men in all ages have been ſo free to part with their credit, to renounce their profit, to lay downe their lives, for ſpirituall things ſake: now did they not apprehend a <hi>reality</hi> and <hi>certainty</hi> in them, ſurely they were no leſſe then mad men, to forgoe <hi>ſubſtances</hi> for <hi>ſhadowes.</hi> It were no leſſe then madneſſe for a man to give himſelfe up to be a priſener, when he might be <hi>free,</hi> to be a <hi>foole</hi> when he might be accounted <hi>wife,</hi> to be <hi>poore</hi> when he might be <hi>rich,</hi> if he did not ſee a <hi>reality</hi> in ſpirituall things for which he willingly forſakes and leaves all theſe other.</p>
            <p>The Saints in all ages have done ſo, wee read in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133226:10"/> Epiſtle to the Hebrew of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> how <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> they forſooke all, <hi>Abraham</hi> forſooke his countrey, <hi>Moſes</hi> forſooke <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, and they were no children; for <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>forty yeares old,</hi> ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when he refuſed the pleaſures of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe to imbrace afflictions with the poore Saints. Whence was this thinke you? <hi>Moſes ſaw him that was inviſible,</hi> how? by faith, for all that chapter hath reference to, and is but an illuſtration of the firſt <hi>verſe: Faith is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> and all the reſt are exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the ſame. <hi>He ſaw him that is inviſible,</hi> and by the ſame eye that he ſaw God, he ſaw all that belonged to God, and therefore ſaw that it was better to <hi>indure afflictions with the people of God, then to injoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that is the reaſon on the other ſide why we ſee all carnall men, and Hypocrites whatſoever, ſome time or other (when in any ſpeciall manner God would have them deny themſelves &amp;c.) to faulter, and flagg, and at laſt fall utterly, which indeed are to be pitied, rather then cenſured by <hi>us men, in the fleſh.</hi> For here is the caſe, there comes a command to a carnall hearted profeſſor (that profeſſeth godlineſſe, but hath not <hi>learned Chriſt, as the truth is in Jeſus)</hi> requiring him to forſake his <hi>credit,</hi> and undergoe <hi>ſhame,</hi> to forſake his <hi>wealth,</hi> and be <hi>poore &amp;c.</hi> this carnall heart having not the <hi>Proſpective-glaſſe</hi> of faith; he ſees not any <hi>reality</hi> in ſpirituall things to <hi>counterpoize</hi> this loſſe, then doth he baſely leave Chriſt, and throw off all his profeſſion. Therefore I ſaid we ſhould pity them, as Chriſt did the young man when he bid him ſell all, he was <hi>ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 22.</note> ſaith the text. If he had ſeen riches in Chriſt, he would have ſold all and rejoiced, and thought he had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133226:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> made a very good bargaine: but I wave theſe things.</p>
            <p>I had another thing, I will onely mention it, becauſe happily the Lord may doe ſome good by it; with all humility I commend it to my brethren, as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We that are Miniſters ſhould in all our Miniſteriall workes, propoſe ſome ſolid ſpirituall ſcope, or end to our Miniſtery, and to every part of it; as</hi> John <hi>did here, and the Apoſtles in every Sermon and Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved,</hi> I have knowne in my obſervation (which it may be hath been too critical in the workes of others) many learned, godly (and otherwiſe able) Miniſters, who took much paines, preached ſolidly, and yet in the end reaped ſome of little little, ſome no appearing fruit at all, of all their ſweat, and labour: ſome of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing in their old age they knew not that ſoule that ever was brought home to Chriſt by their Miniſtry. And this to my apprehenſion ſeemed to be the chiefe reaſon, (as to the worke of man) they never did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any particular <hi>end,</hi> or diſtinct <hi>ſcope</hi> to their worke, which indeed they could not well doe as having no ſpirituall acquaintance with the eſtates and conditions of their Auditors. He that would convert ſinners, or edify Saints, ought to ſtudy ſoules, as well as bookes. And thoſe Miniſters I have obſerved to worke moſt excellently, and labour moſt ſuccesfully, who have been accuſtomed to converſe moſt with their hearers. I have alſo alwaies thought (in reference principally to the diſcharge of my owne worke) that the meere preaching of two Sermons a weeke as it doth not reach the practiſe of the Apoſtles, ſo is <note place="margin">Act. 20. 26.</note> it not one halfe of the worke of a Goſpel Miniſter. As
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133226:11"/> our frequent, familiar ſpirituall converſe with our hearers doth furniſh us with more skill to deale with the ſoules of others, ſo it conduces much to the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our owne, without which wee ſhooting (as it <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 11. 22.</note> were) at rovers muſt often miſſe the marke, if ever we aimed at any: without which we are as expert Smiths that make <hi>curious</hi> keyes and never conſult with the wards of the locke, whereas a rude ilſhap'd key that is fitted to the locke is of much uſe, the other of none at all. This ſurely (might I crave leave to ſpeake) is a comon neglect in us, and a conſiderable defect in moſt of our Miniſtries, which makes many of us <hi>labour</hi> as it were <hi>in the fire.</hi> Neither is it ſufficient for us to ſay, when Gods work doth not proſper in our hands, that yet our <hi>judgemnet is with the Lord &amp;c.</hi> unleſſe we have in <note place="margin">Iſa. 49. 4.</note> all things done the worke of a Miniſter, which as I ſaid before, is not halfe done till wee have attained to ſome compleat meaſure of acquaintance with the ſoules of our people, nor at all will be done till wee have the skill of ſpeaking to their very hearts, and particular eſtates. It was once a ſpeech of a reverend Miniſter, <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth</hi> that bleſſed Apoſtle of South<hi>-wales.</hi>
               </note> who (becauſe of the multitude of his hearers was often neceſſitated to preach in the Ch. yard) <hi>That there was not one perſon in that Congregation whoſe ſpirituall eſtate he did not fully know;</hi> and the ſucceſſe of his worke was anſwerably, exceeding great and glorious: neither (ſaid he) <hi>is there any Sermon I preach, wherein I teach them not at leaſt one leſſon more then any one of them all knew before, and yet I learne from them throughout the weeke, as much or more then they doe of me on the Lords Day.</hi> But (Reverend and beloved) I acknowledge with all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity it becomes me rather to learne, then to teach, onely I beſeech you beare with me thus farre.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:133226:11"/>
            <p> Now to come laſtly, to the leſſon that I ſhall inſiſt on; from the words themſelves: the other leſſons lay but about the words of my text, and were raiſed onely from the coherence. <hi>And truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And theſe things write wee unto you, that your joy may be full.</hi> The leſſon that I would obſerve from theſe words is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulneſſe of joy, is a fruit or conſequent of our fellowſhip with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what this fellowſhip is; to open it at large is not poſſible to be done at this time: I will pitch upon one thing onely therein, and that is a great piece, if not the chiefe in our fellowſhip with God, and Jeſus Chriſt: that is, our <hi>oneneſs</hi> or <hi>union</hi> with the Father and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt: For there can be no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, where there is no union; there can be no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betweene God and us, if wee be not one with him.</p>
            <p>And though fellowſhip with God and Jeſus Chriſt, are not ſeparated in themſelves, and are ſeldom men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in Scripture apart; yet becauſe I would not lay the foundation of my diſcourſe larger and wider, then I have time to build thereon; I muſt therefore crave leave for this time to lay aſide with all reverence, one bleſſed perſon in the Trinity, and ſpeake of our fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to wit, our union with Chriſt, and ſo contract the doctrine to a little narrower compaſſe, thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulneſſe of joy is a fruit of our union with Jeſus</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I contract it to this, as for the times ſake, ſo alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I deſire rather to goe to the bottome of one truth, then to ſtart up many: I will give you two places of Scripture to prove this.</p>
            <p>The firſt is in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. from the beginning to the 12.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133226:12"/> 
               <hi>verſe: I am the vine, and yee are the branches, &amp;c.</hi> you know the parable. <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken to you</hi> (Saith Chriſt) <hi>that my joy may remaine in you, and that your joy might be full.</hi> Underſtand this Scripture (briefly) thus. Our Lord Chriſt was now going to Heaven from his Diſciples, and here in theſe chapters 14. 15. and 16. he takes a great deale of paines to comfort them, to make them as chearefull as he could, in parting with him, and he gives them many bleſſed words of comfort <note place="margin">chap. 16. 23. chap. 14. 13.</note> to feed on, as that <hi>their prayers ſhould be all anſwered:</hi> And though he did goe to Heaven it ſhould further their prayers, and they ſhould have the <hi>Spirit</hi> the ſooner, the <hi>Comforter:</hi> And among the reſt, he tells them, <hi>I am the vine</hi> and <hi>yee are the branches:</hi> there is a world of <note place="margin">chap. 16. 7.</note> comfort and joy in that; though wee goe aſunder and are now to part, yet yee are branches graffed into me, nothing can ſeparate us, <hi>I am the vine, and my Father is the huſbandman,</hi> he will have a care that I nouriſh theſe branches to everlaſting life: and the reaſon wherefore I tell you all this is, <hi>that your joy may be full,</hi> that when I am gone to Heaven, you may for ever remember the <hi>union</hi> that is betweene us, which Heaven and earth and hell ſhall never breake or diſſolve: this is one Scripture for the confirmation of this doctrine.</p>
            <p>The other is in <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 11. compared with <hi>ver.</hi> 13. our Saviour prayeth there, <hi>Holy Father keep them through thine owne Name, thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one as wee are one.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus now prayes for <hi>his</hi> in Heaven, though they know it not but by faith: But here he prayes in their <hi>very hearing</hi> to comfort them. And as Chriſt preached to them that he was one with them, ſo he prayed to his Father in their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that they might be one, and kept one as he is one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133226:12"/> with his Father: whereto is all this? <hi>Theſe things I ſpeake in the world:</hi> why ſo? he might have done it in Heaven; but I doe it in the <hi>world, that they might have my joy fulfilled in themſelves:</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>I know it is an exceeding great joy to my poore diſciples to heare me preach, that I &amp; they are one, but it is more to heare me pray thus for them, for they know, that thou never denyeſt me any thing,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 11. 42.</note> 
               <hi>and I pray, that they and I may be kept one for ever, as thou and I are one.</hi> So much for the proofe of the doctrine. Now I ſhall indeavour to open, and explicate this a little to you; which that I might doe, there are two or three Queſtions, (though I ſhall not be able to reach them all) that would be neceſſary to be reſolved:</p>
            <p>The firſt is this, What is meant by <hi>fulneſſe of</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>joy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, What kind of <hi>union</hi> or <hi>oneneſſe</hi> is this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> that beleivers have with Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>The third is, Wherein doth this <hi>union</hi> ſtand? whereof <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> doth it conſiſt? And I hope by that time. I have opened the firſt, and ſecond, I ſhall not need to ſpeake to the other.</p>
            <p>The firſt Queſtion then is this, what is meant by <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> of joy in this place?</p>
            <p>You muſt underſtand that joy ariſeth alway from <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> the apprehenſion of ſome good, either preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, or hoped for: <hi>Good</hi> is the object of joy, whether that good be really good, or ſeemingly good, whether wee injoy it for preſent, or hope to injoy it hereafter, it workes joy in us. There are 4. ſorts of <hi>good,</hi> and but foure in the world worth mentioning, (I meane of generall good things which may cauſe men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce;) and of thoſe 4, the three firſt will not bring in <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy, they have but a little, ſhort, ſcanty joy with them; &amp; the fourth doth the deed.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:133226:13"/>
            <p> The firſt is <hi>outward mercies,</hi> as health, wealth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, victories, peace, deliverances, &amp;c. Beloved, theſe are outward mercies, temporall mercies, (as we call them) and theſe (I confeſſe) bring in ſome joy to the ſoule, but not full joy; which is true both of the <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of them, or being <hi>inſtrumentall</hi> in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>having</hi> of them: it is comfortable to have peace after warre, and to have plenty, and trading, our ſhops, and high-wayes open &amp;c. wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in theſe things. For godlineſſe doth not <hi>unman</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7 30.</note> us, it doth not hinder the courſe of any <hi>true naturall affection</hi> in us: neither doth God blame us for rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe things. But ſurely the having of theſe things doth not bring in <hi>full joy,</hi> becauſe it is poſſible theſe things may be curſes, as well as bleſſings: and at the beſt they are but <hi>externall temporall</hi> bleſſings, they ſinke not to the bottome of the heart, and they laſt but for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. No, nor being <hi>inſtrumentall in procuring</hi> them. I confeſſe that as the Apoſtle ſaith (citing the words of <note place="margin">Act. 20. 35.</note> our Lord) <hi>it is a more bleſſed thing to give then to receive,</hi> ſo it is a great deale more happy, and a far more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable thing, to be inſtrumentall to procure peace, and welfare to others, then the injoyment of thoſe things our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And this is for your comfort (without flatterie be it ſpoken) I meane our <hi>Parliament</hi> and our <hi>Armyes,</hi> it is much I ſay for your comfort and it may bring a great deale of joy to you, that not onely you have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mercies, as peace &amp;c. but that you have been the chiefe inſtruments to procure all our mercies. And as I ſaid it is a great deale more comfortable to doe good, then to receive it, to be inſtrumentall in procuring theſe things, then the meere having or injoying of them.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133226:13"/> For in Scripture you ſhall finde <hi>Cyrus,</hi> though elſe (it <note place="margin">Eſa. 44. 28.</note> may be) he was a carnall naturall man, yet he is called the <hi>Shepherd</hi> of God, his <hi>Anoynted:</hi> becauſe he was an inſtrument, whereby the Saints injoyed peace and <note place="margin">Eſa. 44. 28.</note> deliverance. You ſhall never reade in Scripture that <note place="margin">Eſa. 45. 1</note> men are called Gods <hi>Anoynted,</hi> ſimply for <hi>having</hi> worldly things: nay, there is ſonmewhat like the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they are called <hi>the men of the world, that have their portion in this life,</hi> and <hi>woe to you that are full.</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 14. Luk. 6. 24. 25.</note> this latter may bring more joy then the other: yet truly, Beloved, it will not bring in, <hi>full</hi> joy: why? becauſe as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of preaching, a man may be a meanes to ſave others, and he himſelfe a <hi>caſtaway;</hi> a <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. ult.</note> man may be as <hi>Noahs</hi> Carpenters, that helped to build an <hi>Arke</hi> for him, and themſelves drowned: therefore though it may bring thee joy, yet if Chriſt be not in thy ſoule, if thou have not union and communion with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt, it will be but a poore comfort to thee to ſay, <hi>I have ſaved a Towne, I have wonne a City, I have ſubdued ſuch an enemy, reduced ſuch a Garriſon, broken ſuch an Army:</hi> this may bring joy, but not <hi>full joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond <hi>good</hi> that men looke on as that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth joy, (which is a little higher then the former,) is the <hi>common gifts and graces</hi> of the Spirit of God, as working of miracles, healing the ſicke, diſpoſſeſſing men of Devills, and thoſe gifts that among us are now extant, as the gift of illumination, prayer, preaching, expounding the Scriptures: and if you looke on theſe things as divided from Chriſt, either the <hi>having</hi> of them, or the exerciſe of them, both theſe things may bring joy, but not <hi>full</hi> joy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>having</hi> of them. <hi>Judas, Simon Magus</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133226:14"/> the diſciples whom our Lord compares to the ſecond and third grounds, had theſe gifts amongſt them, ſome <note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> more, ſome leſſe: and they rejoyced, ſaith the text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. but you know <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith that <hi>the joy of the hypocrites is but for a moment.</hi> And notwithſtanding all theſe gifts, (yea and the performances or plauſible duties which flowe from them) without union with Chriſt men are but hypocrites, wee may call them ſo, and ſo their joy is not <hi>full</hi> being but for a moment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is ſome joy in the <hi>acting</hi> and <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing</hi> of common gifts, and graces, as wee read in <hi>Luk.</hi> where the diſciples had been abroad caſting out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, and rejoycing therein, our Lord checkes them: <hi>In this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>rejoyce not that the ſpirits are ſubject to you,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 10. 20.</note> 
               <hi>but rather rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven.</hi> The meaning is not, you ſhall not at all rejoyce, for Chriſt to have a company of poore fiſhermen perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world, to worke on people ſo as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe them of Devills, to heale the ſicke &amp;c. doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they were in a ſort allowed to rejoyce, but the meaning is this, <hi>Rejoyce not,</hi> that is, expect not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate joy from theſe things, take no ſuch great delight and pleaſure in theſe things, but rather rejoyce that <hi>your names are written in Heaven,</hi> that is, in a manner the ſame as if he had ſaid, that you have union and communion with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>good</hi> thing wee uſe to rejoyce in, is farre higher then this, and yet produceth not <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy, that is, the <hi>ſaving graces of the Spirit</hi> of God. I pray Beloved underſtand me in this warily. There is a great deale of joy ſurely in the <hi>having</hi> or <hi>exerciſing</hi> any <hi>ſaving ſpirituall</hi> grace. Therefore the Apoſtle
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133226:14"/> ſaith, <hi>righteouſneſſe, and peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 1</note> Whereſoever there is <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>peace</hi> in the heart, there <hi>joy</hi> in the holy Ghoſt followes. And in doing any thing out of a ſincere ſpirit, out of the power of grace, there is much joy, which God allowes us. I meet him (ſaith God) that <hi>rejoyceth and worketh righteouſneſſe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 64. 5.</note> There is no act of righteouſneſſe that is done in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but it is as <hi>meate</hi> and <hi>drinke</hi> to us, as our Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 4. yet for all this, there is not, there cannot be <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy from the apprehenſion of any grace, or the exerciſe of it in our ſoules: For if you take grace and abſtract it from our head Chriſt but in your thoughts, and imaginations, (for ſo you may doe) it is but as a dead thing, (as bleſſed <hi>Preſton</hi> ſaith,) it is but a <hi>creature,</hi> and would periſh as other creatures, were we not united to a <hi>Fountaine</hi> of grace, he that hath moſt grace in him, his grace would die and be extinct. Grace is as the beames of the Sun in a houſe through a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: cut off the beames from the Sun, ſhut the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, &amp; they are gon. So I may ſum up all theſe things, and comprehend them (reſpectively) in thoſe words of the Prophet; <hi>Behold al yee that kindle a fire, &amp; compaſſe your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 50. ult.</note> 
               <hi>ſelves about with ſparkes, walke in the light of your fire, and in the ſparkes that yee have kindled. This ſhall yee have of mine hand, yee ſhall lie downe in ſorrow.</hi> Beloved, all theſe put together, certainly make many fine ſparkes of joy, ſome more, ſome leſſe, but if you goe no further, yea (if it were poſſible) that you, who have ſaving grace ſhould riſe no higher, and ſeeke joy no where elſe, all that yee ſhould have at the hand of God in the end would be, yee ſhould lie downe in ſorrow.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, there is a fourth good that brings <hi>indeed fulneſſe</hi> of joy, and that is the <hi>Good</hi> (if I may ſo ſay) that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133226:15"/> is <hi>in God himſelfe by Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> (For wee cannot thinke a thought of God but only in Jeſus Chriſt,) and that, <hi>and that</hi> onely brings <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy.</p>
            <p>If you ask how? It brings it eſpecially 3 wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>this good</hi> is exceeding <hi>full</hi> and perfect, the others are ſcantie, and imperfect. Things fully good bring full comfort and joy. If a man looke on his owne grace, for inſtance, love, he ſhall ſee little of love, but a great deale of envie and hatred: or if there be a little delight in God, there is withall a great deale of awkwardneſſe, and averſneſſe, but if wee looke into the fulneſſe of Chriſt, wee ſhall ſee unſearchable treaſures, riches that have no end. <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the good in Chriſt hath a: <hi>perpetuity</hi> in it; as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>in thy preſence is fulneſſe of joy,</hi> and in <note place="margin">Pſalme 16.</note> the next words, <hi>pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Beloved, there is an end of all the comforts of this world. As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>thoſe that rejoyce ſhould be as though they rejoyced not, they that buy as if they poſſeſſed not, for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>faſhion of this world paſſeth away,</hi> and there will be an utter end of thoſe things that are below: But what is in God, and in Jeſus Chriſt, wil be <hi>full</hi> and <hi>freſh</hi> to all eternity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a Saint hath a <hi>right</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> in all this <hi>Good</hi> to all eternity, and here comes in the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy and not before.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Queſtion for the opening of this truth is this: What manner of <hi>union</hi> this is, that wee have with Jeſus Chriſt, that brings in this fulneſſe of joy?</p>
            <p>For anſwer to that, take notice of theſe 4 things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a very <hi>neere union</hi> that a poore Saint hath with Chriſt: I ſay Saints, becauſe poore ſinners, drunkards, enemies to godlineſſe, they have not yet any ſhare in this union or benefit from it: God may in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133226:15"/> his time give it them; but Saints and beleivers, they have a <hi>neere</hi> union with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You will ſay how neere?</p>
            <p>If an Angel were to ſpeake to you he cannot ſatisfie you fully in this: only as farre as our underſtanding can reach it, and the creatures can ſerve to illuſtrate theſe things, thus. Whatſoever by way of compariſon can be alleadged, concerning the combination of any one thing with another (whatſoever it be in the whole Creation of God) <hi>that,</hi> and much more, may be ſaid of our union with Jeſus Chriſt. To give inſtances out of the Scripture: ſee what one <hi>ſtick</hi> is to another being <hi>glewed</hi> together, ſee what one <hi>friend</hi> is to another, (as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> that are ſaid to be <hi>woven</hi> and <hi>knit</hi> each to other) ſee how neere the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Child</hi> are, how neere the <hi>Huſband</hi> and <hi>Wife</hi> are one to another, ſee what union is betweene the <hi>branches</hi> and the <hi>vine,</hi> the <hi>members</hi> and the <hi>head,</hi> nay one thing more, ſee what the <hi>ſoule</hi> is to the <hi>body, ſuch</hi> is Chriſt and ſo <hi>neere</hi> is he and neerer to the perſon of every true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiver: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I live not, but Chriſt liveth in me,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Jeſus Chriſt is to my ſoule and <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> body, as the ſoule is to the body of a naturall man, that acts &amp; quickens it naturally: Beloved, there is a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>neereneſſe</hi> in this union.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is the moſt <hi>reall</hi> union, theſe things make for our joy, for it was not in vaine that Chriſt ſpake of theſe things before he went to Heaven, that their joy might be full) I ſay it is a moſt <hi>reall</hi> union. As there is a greater <hi>neereneſſe;</hi> ſo there is a greater <hi>reality</hi> in our union with Chriſt, then is betweene any naturall things whatſoever, they are but <hi>ſhadowes</hi> of ſpirituall things. It is not a <hi>notionall</hi> union, as ſome conceive that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133226:16"/> Chriſt and wee are united as the <hi>object</hi> is united to the <hi>underſtanding;</hi> for when a man conceives of any thing, that thing is united in an <hi>abſtracted metaphyſicall</hi> way to the underſtanding: ſo hypocrites may have a great deale of union with Chriſt, they may goe far, and have much knowledge, and light in the apprehenſion of ſpirituall things. You may ſee the difference of this union, by comparing that union an <hi>huſband</hi> hath with his <hi>wife,</hi> and that union which his minde and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hath with any other perſon; it is not as when a mans underſtanding conceiveth of another woman, by meere imagination, and thought of her, there is a kind of union betweene her and his underſtanding: But this is another kind of union that is betweene a man and his wife, by the bond and tye of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> that is a <hi>reall</hi> union, that is conceived by ſome to be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that place <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>I will marry thee in faithfulnes &amp; judgement,</hi> or in <hi>truth,</hi> as ſome read it, I will marry thee in <hi>truth:</hi> I would not have you think the union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and the Saints is nothing but a poore empty <hi>Notion</hi> or <hi>imagination,</hi> but I will marry thee in <hi>truth, (i.)</hi> thou ſhalt be my wiſe in <hi>reality,</hi> as much, or rather more <hi>really,</hi> then man and wife are united by Marriage.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a <hi>totall</hi> union that is betweene Jeſus Chriſt and his poore Saints: (Oh, this is full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort if you looke on it ſpiritually) that is, <hi>whole</hi> Chriſt is united to the <hi>whole beleever,</hi> ſoule and body. Thou haſt all Chriſt, whatſoever thou canſt conceive to be in the Father, or in Jeſus Chriſt, 'tis really and wholly thine: as I could give inſtances had I time out of Scripture. Thou art one with him in his <hi>Nature,</hi> in his <hi>Name,</hi> thou haſt the ſame <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:133226:16"/> in thee as he hath, the ſame <hi>precious promiſes,</hi> the ſame <hi>acceſſe to God by prayer</hi> as he, thou haſt the ſame <hi>love of the Father,</hi> all that he did or ſuffered thou haſt a ſhare in it, all is thine, thou haſt his <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith; ſo on thy part he hath thee <hi>wholly,</hi> thy <note place="margin">Cor. 4.</note> 
               <hi>nature,</hi> thy <hi>ſinnes, the puniſhment of thy ſinnes,</hi> thy <hi>wrath,</hi> thy <hi>curſe,</hi> thy <hi>ſhame;</hi> ſo he would have thee all, thy <hi>wit,</hi> thy <hi>wealth,</hi> thy <hi>ſtrength,</hi> all that thou <hi>art,</hi> or <hi>haſt,</hi> and <hi>canſt doe</hi> for him, ſo thou haſt Jeſus Chriſt: It is a <hi>totall</hi> union, <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am his,</hi> whole Chriſt from top to toe is mine, and all that I <hi>am, have</hi> or <hi>can doe,</hi> for evermore is his, it is <hi>totall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is an <hi>inſeparable</hi> union, it can never be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. <hi>I will make</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>an everlaſting Covenant with them, that I will not turne away from them, to doe them good, I will put my feare in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me Jeremiah</hi> 32. This is a glorious word, but the poore Chriſtian will ſay, Tis true, thou wilt not turne away from me, I know thou wilt not, but I ſhall turne away from thee. I turne every day towards ſin and <hi>Satan.</hi> Why, ſaith God, <hi>I will put my feare in thy heart, tbat thou ſhalt not turne away from me,</hi> we ſhall be kept together for evermore, and never ſeparated. Thence <hi>Paul</hi> triumphantly challenges al enemies in heaven, (or rather in Hell,) to doe their worſt to breake this knot; <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt? ſhall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>diſtreſſe, famine &amp;c?</hi> come all that can together, and ſee if that bleſſed <hi>union</hi> betwene me &amp; Chriſt, ſhall ever be broken or diſſolved by all that you can doe.</p>
            <p>Now (Beloved) a word, or two of Uſe. I will wave the other Queſtion, that happily would be neceſſary for the further opening of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> becauſe I will not weary you: you ſee what <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of joy is, and what
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133226:17"/> this <hi>union</hi> is: and by what you have heard already you may eaſily convince your ſelves, that <hi>fellowſhip and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Jeſus Chriſt, will bring fulneſſe of joy to the ſoule.</hi> The uſes are theſe briefly.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this, you may hence behold (if the Lord <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> open your eyes, for ſo it muſt be) what a glorious ſtate and condition God hath placed a Chriſtian in, a poore Saint, be he never ſo meane, or miſerable otherwiſe in the eye of the world: his condition what is it? He is one with Jeſus Chriſt, as Chriſt is one with the Father. There is a bleſſed place in <hi>Zachary</hi> where Jeſus Chriſt is called Gods fellow. <hi>Awake oh ſword againſt my ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 13. 7.</note> 
               <hi>againſt the man my fellow,</hi> Chriſt is one with the Father, he is his <hi>fellow,</hi> and every Saint is Chriſt's fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: he is <hi>anointed with the oyle of gladneſſe above his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 7.</note> 
               <hi>fellowes.</hi> Chriſt is Gods <hi>fellow,</hi> and wee are Chriſt's <hi>fellowes.</hi> There is a kind of <hi>analogicall proportion</hi> (not <hi>Geometricall</hi> of equalitie, as they call it) betweene Chriſt and Saints in every thing: run them over in your thoughts, and take a view of all Chriſt, what he is in his <hi>Perſon,</hi> in his <hi>glory,</hi> in his <hi>Spirit,</hi> in his <hi>graces,</hi> in his <hi>Fathers love,</hi> and in the <hi>acceſſe</hi> he hath to the Father, in all theſe with what more you can imagine in Chriſt, wee are in a ſort <hi>fellowes</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>Only with this difference (that you may not ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) Chriſt hath the <hi>preheminence</hi> in all things, every <note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> thing in its owne order, <hi>The Father is above all, and wee by him:</hi> all comes from the Father firſt to Jeſus Chriſt, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> and all wee have is by <hi>Marriage</hi> with Ieſus Chriſt, and wee muſt abide in our union with Chriſt, as he doth abide with his Father. Moreover betweene him and the perſon of the Father, there is an <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> union, and ours is virtuall by the power of the Spirit of God; he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133226:17"/> by his union hath all good things without meaſure, and wee by ours in meaſure: as it pleaſeth him to diſtribute. But excepting theſe things, Jeſus Chriſt and wee are <hi>fellowes,</hi> for ſo God calls us.</p>
            <p>Therefore (Beloved) did but the Lord by his holy Spirit unvaile all your eyes, and give you but one glance of what the eſtate of a Saint is, that is united to Jeſus Chriſt, who in this place would not be a Saint? who would not be a Chriſtian? who would be a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, a ſwearer, a perſecuter of godlineſſe? who, I ſay, would be ſuch a one, that knowes the treaſure, riches, and happineſſe of a Saint in Chriſt? our ignorance of this makes men refuſe Chriſt, and goe on in ſin. For every man naturally bargaines (as he apprehends) for his gaine, and never for his loſſe: that is the reaſon I ſay, that we bargaine not for Heaven and for Chriſt, becauſe wee thinke it is for our loſſe, and this becauſe God hath not opened our eyes to ſee the <hi>unſearchable riches</hi> and <hi>treaſures</hi> that are in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Beſides, were the happineſſe of a Saint rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and ſeriouſly conſidered, who would be a back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlider? you heare what a Saint is, he can goe and ſay to his ſoule and his fellow Saints, <hi>our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Who would relinquiſh Chriſt and all in him for ſome baſe luſt? O ſaith the Author of the Epiſt. to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> let there not <hi>be a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 16.</note> 
               <hi>prophane man &amp;c. Eſau</hi> was a prophane man, he had godly parents, and was religiouſly educated, yet the Apoſtle calls him prophane, why? becauſe for a little <hi>morſell</hi> he ſold his <hi>birth-right;</hi> and there is a farre greater diſproportion betweene the riches of Chriſt, and the baſe luſts that wee hanker after, then betweene <hi>Eſaus</hi> inheritance and <hi>Jacobs</hi> pottage; therefore looke
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133226:18"/> to your ſelves in theſe things, you that are <hi>ancient Profeſſors,</hi> who begin to backſlide apace, and take this as a meanes to help thee when thou goeſt to get ſuch a ones favour, to make ſuch a one thy friend, to get ſuch an office, and the like, wherein thou muſt yeild to ſin, and joyne with ſinners in their wicked deſignes, ſee what a <hi>bargaine</hi> thou makeſt: Thou relinquiſheſt Chriſt Jeſus, and all thy portion in him, to purchaſe theſe vaine frivolous things.</p>
            <p>Another Uſe I will touch but briefely, this is the reaſon, why the Lord takes it ſo well or ill at our hands <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> that wee uſe his people kindly or unkindly; why ſhould the Lord be ſo much offended to ſee his <hi>poore</hi> Saints (that are ready to beg at your doores,) oppreſſed and wronged, perſecuted, &amp;c? becauſe <hi>even they</hi> are one with Jeſus Chriſt. That is the reaſon why on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, he takes it ſo kindly that wee doe any thing for them, that wee be tender and carefull of the good of his poore Saints, becauſe it is <hi>to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: <hi>He that beſtowes a cup of cold water to one of his little ons in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 42.</note> 
               <hi>name of a diſciple, ſhall not loſe his reward.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>he that receiveth you receiveth me,</hi> that is the reaſon; ſo in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>I was hungry and you fed me, naked and you cloathed me, thirſty and you gave me drinke: When did we ſee thee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <hi>hungry or thirſty or naked? In as much as yee have done it to the leaſt of my members, yee did it to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See on the contrary, he that <hi>toucheth</hi> a Saint <hi>toucheth the apple of Gods eye.</hi> And the reaſon he is ſo angry is, <note place="margin">Zach. 2. 8.</note> becauſe now the Father, and Jeſus Chriſt, and the pooreſt Saint, are really and totally one, each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſtrike at one, ſtrike at all. Therefore I beſeech you make this uſe of it, <hi>be kind to the poore Saints,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their meanneſſe, outward weakneſſes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133226:18"/> and frailties, though they bee poore, baſe, and vile, yet they have a glorious <hi>head</hi> and <hi>Husband.</hi> Thou thinkeſt it is an eaſie thing to ſuppreſſe a poore Saint, to overthrow him, and overcome him: and indeed it were ſo, but that he hath a great partie in Heaven, greater then all the world, therefore <hi>there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Sermon.</note> 
               <hi>againſt Iſrael,</hi> as you heard from the Lord this morning.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I would give you (in theſe times when every body ſpeakes of reformation of Religion, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> and the like) one word of direction, in point of Church fellowſhip, or communion, one with another, <hi>(i.)</hi> Take heed you doe not make any <hi>outward exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> thing, the <hi>maine pillar</hi> and foundation of your Church-fellowſhip, of your Chriſtian Communion. As <hi>(v. g.)</hi> if any ſhould conceive the way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a Church to be by an <hi>externall Covenant,</hi> a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall confeſſion, baptizing</hi> this way, or that way, (I meane by dipping, or ſprinkling) or by <hi>conjunction</hi> of <hi>opinion</hi> in ſome controverted point: <hi>(I</hi> doe not at this time condemne or commend any of theſe things for the matter of them, but only this I drive at) if you build your Chriſtian fellowſhip and communion upon any one of theſe things, or ſuch like, making them the <hi>maine pillar</hi> of Chriſtian communion; it will be more like a carnall faction, then a ſpirituall communion.</p>
            <p>Take therefore the Apoſtles rule in the text, <hi>we have fellowſhip with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And what followes? <hi>theſe things wee write, tbat you may have fellowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> That is the maine and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ground of all Church fellowſhip, of Chriſtian fellowſhip, of the Saints one with another. Therefore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133226:19"/> when I have communion with a Saint, I muſt not looke <hi>ſo much</hi> whether he be of ſuch an opinion, or whether he have taken the Covenant, or have been baptized <note n="*" place="margin">I ſpeake not this as if my opinion were for rebaptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or againſt the baptizing of the infants of beleevers, the contrary appeares by my practiſe: but only, that ſuch difference of opinion ſhould not hinder their mutuall recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who are in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God and Ieſus Chriſt.</note> once or twice or ten times, but ſee if he have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Father, and with Jeſus Chriſt; if he hath, he is one of the body, and a fellow-member, and wee muſt fall in immediately with him; though withall, I am to uſe all meanes, in love and meekneſſe, to recall him from his error according to the rules of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how ſhall it be knowne that he is ſuch a one?</p>
            <p>I will name but two generall rules, the beſt, and the cleareſt that I know in the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſatisfie you in that.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place conſult with that in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>not holding the head,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. That is, when a man ſees a Chriſtian, for <hi>matter of doctrine, judgement</hi> or <hi>opinion,</hi> to hold the <hi>head</hi> Jeſus Chriſt to be the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> and <hi>juſtification</hi> by him, <hi>ſanctification</hi> from him, according to the Scriptures &amp;c. though in externall things, it may be he doth not as yet ſee this or that Government ſo cleare in the word, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtantiall truth controverted amongſt the Saints, (theſe and ſuch like things cut him not off from the head) theſe things doe not <hi>un-Saint</hi> him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. And therefore woe be to thee if thou reject him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond rule is laid downe in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing my text; if <hi>ye walke in the light,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle you have fellowſhip: <hi>(q. d.)</hi> Brethren I would have you to have fellowſhip with us: <hi>But if we walke in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wee lye, and doe not the truth: but if wee walke in the light as he is in the light, wee have fellowſhip one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:133226:19"/> What is this light? It is holineſſe of life and converſation. <hi>If a man doeth righteouſneſſe he is borne of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. as if he had ſaid, this is the rule that I goe by, he that walks with God, calls on his name, teacheth his family, hates that which is evill, takes paines in that which is good, &amp;c. him I account to be a man that is <hi>borne of God, he walkes in the light,</hi> with whom I ought to have fellowſhip and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Beloved, I had many more Uſes, as to examine our ſelves by what I have ſaid, whether wee have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt: whether the Image of Chriſt be on us: have wee his graces? are wee like Chriſt? remember that word <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. which will ſound terrible in thine eares when thou comeſt to dye, <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his:</hi> haſt thou the Spirit of Chriſt? did Chriſt walke, and talke, and plot, and deſigne againſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God as thou doeſt? Remember if thou be one with Chriſt, thou haſt the ſame <hi>Image,</hi> the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> the ſame <hi>Grace,</hi> the ſame <hi>life,</hi> in a word, <hi>thou doeſt not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>live but Ieſus Chriſt liveth in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may comfort us alſo, (if wee apprehend it ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually) if wee be <hi>poore,</hi> wee are married to one that is <hi>rich;</hi> if <hi>full</hi> of <hi>wants,</hi> there is <hi>a fulneſſe</hi> in Chriſt to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply us; if <hi>tempted</hi> by <hi>Satan,</hi> in him wee are <hi>more then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, wee ſhall tread Satan under feet;</hi> if trampled on <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 20.</note> by the world, yet wee are Kings and Queenes. The ſame <hi>annointing</hi> that is powred on him the head, <hi>runs downe to the ſkirts of his garments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it ſhould be an incitement to all of us who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelves believers, to walke in the light, to walke as thoſe that are married to Chriſt: Doeth it become a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133226:20"/> Sonne of God, a member of Chriſt, to be proud, to be froward, to ſharke, to cheate to be a worldling, as many profeſſors in this adulterous generation are? walke therefore I pray as children of the light. And ſo I have done.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will ſay, What is this to <hi>Oxford, Farringdon,</hi> or <hi>Worceſter,</hi> the buſineſſe of the day? Truly Beloved, Jeſus Chriſt is good for all things, at all times. And as touching the mercy of God in theſe things to us and the Kingdome, the Lord hath been pleaſed to teach you this morning more largely and fully then I am able to doe, the Lord ſanctifie it to you and me: a few words indeed I had concerning that ſubject, but they are for the moſt part, ſpoken to you already by our Reverend Brother, therefore I ſhall but touch upon them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a word of information to us all (I am ſure I have it from the Lord, and his word) that wee learne from our mercies, <hi>(Oxford</hi> eſpecially) <hi>that every proud and high thing that exalts it ſelfe againſt Chriſt and his people, God will throw downe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I my ſelfe was a ſpectator, an eye-witneſſe, when the Lord delivered that City, that Univerſity, into the hands of our Army: and being there I did ſtudy and ſtrive according to the ſmall portion of grace I had received, to meditate what I might learne for Gods glory and the good of my ſoule from that buſineſſe; and amongſt all the meane thoughts I had, <hi>this</hi> came in with the greateſt glory into my ſoule, that beholding that Univerſity that I had formerly knowne and heard much of lately, I was filled with admiration, to ſee how all the <hi>pride of that place was brought downe in one day.</hi> Thought I ſurely the <hi>deſigne of God in theſe dayes,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:133226:20"/> 
               <hi>is to bring downe one proud thing after another, that exalts it ſelfe againſt Chriſt.</hi> It was a gallant Univerſity; what a ſtrong impregnable Garriſon was it alſo? There was all the <hi>Military</hi> art of the Kingdom, there was the <hi>Law, learning, policy,</hi> and <hi>wit</hi> of the Kingdome, and ſome conceive the <hi>wealth</hi> of the Kingdome too had for a long while been there alſo, there was <hi>line</hi> upon <hi>line,</hi> and <hi>Bulwarke</hi> upon <hi>Bulwarke,</hi> and <hi>fence</hi> upon <hi>fence;</hi> and it was the very <hi>Center</hi> of all the enemies of God; when they had been routed abroad, or frighted at home, then preſently away to <hi>Oxford</hi> as to a ſure <hi>refuge:</hi> yet <hi>Oxford</hi> though it were never ſo <hi>rich,</hi> ſo <hi>learned,</hi> ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,</hi> ſo <hi>filled</hi> with <hi>Princes, Nobles, fineſt witted ſchollers,</hi> and <hi>beſt skilled ſoldiers,</hi> moſt <hi>experienced Politicians,</hi> though it was the very <hi>Queene</hi> of England, yet <hi>Oxford</hi> it muſt ſtoope downe and fall.</p>
            <p>And in theſe times for my part I apprehend nothing (with more cleareneſſe and evidence) of Gods mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all his worke in theſe dayes, then that it is <hi>his glorious deſigne to bring downe every high looke,</hi> and <hi>every</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Oh thou op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of God &amp; godlineſſe lay this to heart.</note> 
               <hi>proud thing that exalts it ſelfe againſt Chriſt.</hi> Theſe are the laſt times, read <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2. you ſhall ſee it at large: and wee have ſeen by experience alſo what courſe God hath taken with many. You know foure or five yeares agoe, off goes the head of one great man, then a little afterwards ſome others aroſe, and downe they goe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And now at <hi>Oxford,</hi> they had as I ſaid, <hi>art, wit,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength, policy, nobility, wealth,</hi> and what not but <hi>Grace?</hi> (which were the very words of ſome of them,) and where are they? Take it for a truth of God, if any <note place="margin">☜</note> ſtart up yet in their roome, if any grove grow up to eclipſe Gods glory, or ſhadow his houſe, if any <hi>thing</hi> or <hi>perſon</hi> will exalt it ſelfe againſt Chriſt, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133226:21"/> it is Gods purpoſe and glorious deſigne to cut them off, God will bring them downe to the duſt.</p>
            <p>Learne therefore to walke humbly before the Lord, and doe not ſtrive any longer againſt the ſtreame; and though the Lord have given you ſuch power and peace that you have no enemies, yet take heed leaſt any of you ſtep up in their ſtead; for be aſſured, be you never ſo great, (as God is in Heaven, and wee are on earth,) that <hi>man, family, faction,</hi> or <hi>crew,</hi> that will goe about to oppoſe God or his people, God will throw them downe: lie low therefore on the ground, and give glory to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I had alſo a word of exhortation, but my Brother hath prevented me, and ſpoke moſt of my thoughts concerning that already, only if you will give me leave to minde you, I deſire you <hi>to take heed of provoking that God, who hath done all this for you.</hi> I will inſtance in two or three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I am afraid ſome of you make <hi>too much haſt to be rich,</hi> now <hi>trading, Cuſtomers, Offices &amp;c.</hi> come in; <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 20.</note> Oh pauſe a while and conſider what God hath done, and whence he hath raiſed you, and make a ſpirituall improvement of that firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, oh that you would be exhorted now to heare the cauſe of the poore, and the widow, oh that you would be like <hi>Job</hi> who <hi>made the widowes heart to ſing:</hi> O he is a bleſſed Magiſtrate, a bleſſed Parliament-man, <note place="margin">Iob. 19. 13.</note> a Prince, a King, that can ſay ſo, <hi>I made the poore widowes heart to ſing,</hi> I did take their Petitions, and would have them <hi>read,</hi> &amp; did <hi>ſee</hi> ſomething done in the Committees before I gave over, and not trifle out the time; when peoples <hi>livelyhoods</hi> and <hi>lives</hi> were at the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133226:21"/> ſtate, I have not been of thoſe whoſe profeſſion is to give only faire words, and yet doe nothing for their reliefe; I deſire with humility that you would take that, as an admonition from the Lord.</p>
            <p>And then take heed of inſiſting too much upon <hi>formes.</hi> Truly I am not of their opinion that would <hi>ſublimate</hi> Religion into airy <hi>notions</hi> and <hi>Chimaraes</hi> out of all <hi>forme,</hi> but yet take heed that you <hi>inſiſt not too much: (i.)</hi> ſo as to loſe the power of godlineſſe while you purſue the forme. The Saints in <hi>England</hi> doubtleſſe heretofore, though they had leſſe <hi>beauty</hi> by reaſon of the want of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>government</hi> then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches beyond-ſea, yet they had (as you were not long ſince ſweetly taught in this place) more <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Tho. Goodwins</hi> Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Houſe of Com. <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. 1645.</note> &amp; power, then moſt reformed Churches a broad: and it is much to be feared, if we our ſelves now, were compared with our ſelves heretofore, wee ſhould bee found to have more <hi>power, holineſſe, truth, love</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> in Gods ſervice heretofore then now wee have. Therefore take heed that out of zeale to ſet up a <hi>forme of Government</hi> &amp;c. you doe not forgoe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the <hi>power of godlineſſe</hi> the while.</p>
            <p>Another thing I would take the boldneſſe to minde you of, (now we are in peace,) is, to haſten to the help of our Brethren: you know what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to the <note place="margin">Num. 32.</note> two Tribes, when they ſtaied on the further ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> you have gotten fine <hi>ſeates</hi> for your ſelves, and you will build <hi>houſes</hi> and <hi>ſheepfolds</hi> for your cattell &amp;c. you will let your brethren goe over to fight, while you ſit here; this was the manner <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> of your Fathers to provoke the Lord, but if you doe ſo <hi>be ſure your ſin</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ver. 33.</note> 
               <hi>will find you out.</hi> So I ſay unto you, if you will now goe and build <hi>houſes,</hi> and ſettle your ſelves in the world &amp;c.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133226:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> and will not ſend over for the <hi>effectuall</hi> reliefe of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though you lie never ſo cloſe and ſafe, <hi>your ſin will finde you out,</hi> this ſin will hunt you as a hound; (ſo the alluſion is) it will <hi>lye at the doore</hi> as a Maſtiffe at the threſhold. Therefore as the Lord hath begun to <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> ſmile upon us, and to cauſe the Sun to ſhine upon <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (upon a great part of it at leaſt) oh forget not poore <hi>bleeding Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what if you ſhould ſpend one ſingle thought upon <hi>poore contemptible Wales?</hi> it's little indeed, and as little reſpected, yet time was the enemy made no ſmall uſe and advantage of it, how inconſiderable ſoever wee deeme it; oh let not poore <hi>Wales</hi> continue <hi>ſighing famiſhing, mourning</hi> and <hi>bleeding,</hi> while you have your daies of <hi>Feaſting, rejoycing, Thanksgiving</hi> and <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> God. Oh how loath I am to mention it to you? is it not a ſad caſe that <hi>in thirteene Counties there ſhould not be above</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">God grant there be more I Know not ſo many.</note> 
               <hi>thirteene conſcientious Miniſters who in theſe times expreſſed themſelves firmly and conſtantly faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Parliament, and formerly preached profitably in the Welch Language</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The general practice of Godly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> 
               <hi>twice every Lords Day?</hi> Yet (praiſed be our God) ſome few there be (though I my ſelfe am unworthy to be reckoned amongſt them) who are ready and willing to <hi>ſpend</hi> and be <hi>ſpent</hi> for the glory of God, and the good of their countrey: oh that you would allow them ſome ſmall competency of maintenance for their incouragement; be it, if you pleaſe, but meere food and rayment. That little eſtate they had is waſted for their ſincere affection to your ſervice, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (may I crave leaue to ſpeake it) as it would be a worke of <hi>piety</hi> in you to ſend them forth to preach, ſo alſo a worke of <hi>equity,</hi> you ſhould relieve them and provide for them.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:133226:22"/>
            <p> But laſt of all, let that be now my exhortation, which is my conſtant petition both publiquely and privately to the Lord, for the Honourable Members of both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Let faith and patience have their perfect worke in you.</hi> That is, you may perhaps ſee new troubles ariſe, Satan may rage yet more then ever, (the laſt times will ſurely be the worſt) bee not weary of well doing, let not your hands or hearts fall by any diſcouragement you may meet withall; you have had a <hi>world of experience,</hi> how God hath helped you and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded your enemies, how oft hath he brought them to ruine even by their owne deſignes? beware therefore of <hi>unbeleife,</hi> if you come into any new ſtraites, never <hi>faulter</hi> any more, but truſt perfectly in that God that hath hitherto never failed you, who hath wrought many a glorious ſalvation and deliverance for you, (which wee here behold and celebrate this day) to whom be praiſe and glory evermore through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
